A Finding Aid to the Duane Michals Papers, circa 1940-2019, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Duane Michals papers
circa 1940-2019
Archives of American Art
Michals, Duane
AAA.michduan
Archival Resource Key
7.5 Linear feet
The papers of New York based photographer Duane Michals date from circa 1940-2019 and measure 7.5 linear feet. This small collection includes Michals' correspondence from the 1970s, printed material, photographs of Michals, as well as photographic prints he has taken for commercial and artistic projects. There is a 6.3 linear foot unprocessed addition to this collection donated 2019 and 2020 that includes primarily photographs taken by Michals of actors, writers, friends, family and classmates; photo books, postcards, assemblages, photo-sequences by Michals; an Yves St. Laurent portfolio; and photographs of Michals. Additional material includes biographical information, correspondence, printed material and a catalog on CD.
Scope and Contents
The papers of New York based photographer Duane Michals date from circa 1940-2019 and measure 7.5 linear feet. This small collection includes Michals' correspondence from the 1970s, printed material, photographs of Michals, as well as photographic prints he has taken for commercial and artistic projects. There is a 6.3 linear foot unprocessed addition to this collection donated 2019 and 2020 that includes primarily photographs taken by Michals of actors, writers, friends, family and classmates; photo books, postcards, assemblages, photo-sequences by Michals; an Yves St. Laurent portfolio; and photographs of Michals. Additional material includes biographical information, correspondence, printed material and a catalog on CD.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as four series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1967-2010 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 2: Printed Material, circa 1970-2015 (0.2 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 3: Photographs, circa 1960-2015 (0.5 linear feet; Box 2, OV 3-6)
Series 4: Unprocessed Addition, circa 1940-2019 (6.3 linear feet; Boxes 7-13, 16-18, OV 14-15)
Biographical / Historical
Duane Michals (1932- ) is a photographer in New York, New York. Born and raised in Pennsylvania, Michals received his Bachelor's degree from the University of Denver in 1953, after which he served for two years in the Army. In 1956 he moved to New York City, and began studying graphic design at Parsons School of Design. Although he did not complete his studies there, he developed an interest in photography and began working as a commercial photographer for magazines. In addition to his commercial work, Michals has been exhibiting his photographs in galleries and museums since the 1960s.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the Archives of American Art by Duane Michals in 2015, 2019, and 2020.
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Duane Michals conducted by Christopher Lyon in 2016.
Photographers -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs
- Correspondence, 1967-2010; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence dates from 1967-2010 is both personal and professional. The bulk consists of letters to Michals from 1972-1977, although a few drafts of outgoing letters are also found here. Notable correspondents include photographers Berenice Abbott, Ralph Gibson, Les Krims, Gerard Malanga, Eve Sonneman, and Arthur Tress. Professional correspondence is with magazines, museums, and galleries, and pertains to work for hire, publication permissions, exhibitions, and requests for appearances. A draft of Michals' text "Real Dreams" was sent to a friend for review, and is filed with the 1976 correspondence.
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1967; 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Correspondence, circa 2005-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Printed Material, circa 1970-2015; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  Printed material dates from circa 1970-2015 and documents Michals' career through announcements, clippings, exhibition catalogs, and press releases. A book featuring Michals, and a few other printed items including brochures, a program, and an essay about Michals' work are also found here.
  - Book, Duane Michals Steals a Book by Erik LaPrade, 2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Announcements, circa 1970-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, circa 1970; 2000-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Guides, 2008-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Press Releases, circa 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Other Printed Matter, 2003-2010; circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Photographs, circa 1960-2015; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 2, OV 3-6
  Photographs date from circa 1960-2015 and are both of and by Michals. The first folder here includes snapshots of Michals at exhibitions and with family and friends. The remainder of the folders contain Michals' working prints from photographic series for various commercial and artistic projects.
  - Photographs of Duane Michals at Exhibitions and with Family and Friends, 1976; 2005-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs by Duane Michals, Assorted, circa 1960-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Advertising Campaign for Eli Lilly, circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 3)
  - Advertising Campaign for Eli Lilly, circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4)
  - Black and White Photographs with Handwritten Text, 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 5)
  - Color Photographs, Still Lifes, 2006; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 6)
- Unprocessed Addition, circa 1940-2019; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 6.3 Linear feet Boxes 7-13, 16-18, OV14-15
  The 6.3 linear foot unprocessed addition to this collection donated 2019 and 2020 includes primarily photographs taken by Michals of actors, writers, friends, family and classmates; photo books, postcards, assemblages, photo-sequences by Michals; an Yves St. Laurent portfolio; and photographs of Michals. Additional material includes biographical information, correspondence, printed material and a catalog on CD.
  - Unprocessed Addition, circa 1940-2019; Archival Resource Key (Box 7)
  - Unprocessed Addition, circa 1940-2019; Archival Resource Key (Box 8)
  - Unprocessed Addition, circa 1940-2019; Archival Resource Key (Box 9)
  - Unprocessed Addition, circa 1940-2019; Archival Resource Key (Box 10)
  - Unprocessed Addition, circa 1940-2019; Archival Resource Key (Box 11)
  - Unprocessed Addition, circa 1940-2019; Archival Resource Key (Box 12)
  - Unprocessed Addition, circa 1940-2019; Archival Resource Key (Box 13)
  - Unprocessed Addition, circa 1940-2019; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 14)
  - Unprocessed Addition, circa 1940-2019; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 15)
  - Unprocessed Addition, circa 1982-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 16)
  - Unprocessed Addition, circa 1982-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 17)
  - Unprocessed Addition, circa 1982-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 18)